<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-11-06T22:48:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jeremy Nixon</title><subtitle>Reach to the sky from the bottom.</subtitle><author><name>Jeremy Nixon</name></author><entry><title type="html">Information Cascades and Independent Thought</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/09/26/cascades-independent-thought.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Information Cascades and Independent Thought" /><published>2019-09-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-09-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/09/26/cascades-independent-thought</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/09/26/cascades-independent-thought.html">&lt;p&gt;One of the most important conceptual advances in understanding spreading and diffusion was the concept of critical thresholds leading to cascades. An idea / innovation either dies out shortly or increases exponentially until it saturates the graph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cascade, or a threshold above which some information spreads deeply through a social network, implies that the information we see is the information that is capable of triggering a cascade, whose inverse implies that we do not see information (which may be true, and valuable!) that fails to cross the critical threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is that there are many true, valuable insights in immediate reach of any independently thinking mind. Low hanging fruit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the novel argument for independent thought - it’s not valuable because you reach the unthinkable contrarian truth nobody else could have seen. It’s valuable because it lets you reach the low hanging fruit that didn’t catch the attention of the cascades across your social network.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jeremy Nixon</name></author><summary type="html">One of the most important conceptual advances in understanding spreading and diffusion was the concept of critical thresholds leading to cascades. An idea / innovation either dies out shortly or increases exponentially until it saturates the graph.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Belief in Change for the Non-Believer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/08/03/priors.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Belief in Change for the Non-Believer" /><published>2019-08-03T18:25:46-07:00</published><updated>2019-08-03T18:25:46-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/08/03/priors</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/08/03/priors.html">&lt;p&gt;Say some fantastic intervention comes along. 
Having clear long terms goals is an easy example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ton of people will survey the people they deem to have been successful and ask them, so what was your pathway?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take the simple heuristic of looking at the behavior of successful people and mimicking what they’ve done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say that by default, 95% of people don’t go through life with clear long term goals laid out in front of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5% do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say that this is one of the most effective interventions conceivable. If you set clear long term goals, you have a 100% chance of success. If you don’t, you have a 10% chance of success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will see that only a third of the final population has set clear long term goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may convince you that you’re more likely to succeed than not by not setting clear long term goals, even though it pushes success probability from 10% to 100%!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This horrifying pattern repeats itself across almost every intervention, most of which are rare. When you look at the final succeeding population, averaging over their behavior is a truly awful heuristic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask what happens by default, first and foremost. And discount it. Discount it deeply. Seeing it spread throughout the final, successful population says more about what the predominant behavior was than it says about whether that behavior is genuinely helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I run into counterarguments to obviously valuable interventions (things like planning, being systematic, creating habits, wake time / bedtimes, social accountability, time and focus tracking) and they’re often backed by the sense that few successful people are doing them or advocate for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is our emotional backing for almost all of our decisions - association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All we tend to feel is whether or not we’ve seen the intervention and success co-occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the step forward in thinking style is from associative mode to causal mode.
In causal mode, so many interventions will occur to you that (often) you’ve never heard anybody try before but which would obviously work if they were done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This essay is being written during a 16h back-to-back-to-back writing session.
Obvious intervention.
I’ve heard of nobody who’s tried it.
But this wasn’t driven by associative thinking. It was driven by causal thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evaluation of interventions needs to be counterfactual - all you care about is what would have happened otherwise. Somebody much less successful than you may have an intervention which took them from clearly incapable of performing to performing, which will absolutely work for you if you can release yourself from associative mode. You need the interventions that explain the differences between who they are and who they would have been, rather than their overall average level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free your causal mind to power a rise never seen before.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jeremy Nixon</name></author><summary type="html">Say some fantastic intervention comes along. Having clear long terms goals is an easy example.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Distinctions in Conceptual Style</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/08/03/conceptual-archetypes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Distinctions in Conceptual Style" /><published>2019-08-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-08-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/08/03/conceptual-archetypes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/08/03/conceptual-archetypes.html">&lt;p&gt;You can see a conceptual style as the weighting over particular kinds of mental motion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recombination of weightings over mental motions creates a huge space of possible styles, but in reality it can be compressed into a few archetypes (convergent due to both mimesis and targeting similar goals)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every major statistical concept can be seen as a tendency in conceptual style. Preferring linear vs. nonlinear models. Normal vs. power law distributions. Maximizing thought’s expected value vs. variance vs. skewness vs. kurtosis. Noticing overfitting (usually due to insufficient data) and correcting. Noticing a dearth of data and gathering more. Being well calabrated about confidence (vs. not). And on and on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Associative vs. Causal thinking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Empiricism vs. Rationalism
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What empirically works vs. what should work, or what is consistent&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Narrative vs. Conceptual / Analytic / Statistical&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Critical / Skeptical vs. Application / Building on / Recombination (Yes and)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Re-framing as a constructive version of the skeptical / critical mindset, which questions and replaces assumptions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Working in the same direction with different assumptions, hopefully maintaining shared purpose&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ontology / Paradigm Questioning (There’s an interconnected memeplex of assumptions)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Breakdown of Categories (seeing their brokenness, oneness, or decomposition)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding Complexity (distinctions, conditionals, decomposing) vs. Compressing to Simplicity (unifying, abstracting, synthesizing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Jeremy Nixon</name></author><summary type="html">You can see a conceptual style as the weighting over particular kinds of mental motion.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Becoming Sufficiently Meta</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/08/03/becomming-sufficienlty-meta.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Becoming Sufficiently Meta" /><published>2019-08-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-08-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/08/03/becomming-sufficienlty-meta</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/08/03/becomming-sufficienlty-meta.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;meta-modeling&quot;&gt;Meta-Modeling&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are frames that I can use for generating and improving models of systems or topics. There are plenty of examples in Modeled Systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Model - Technique framing -
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Take techniques that work, and let the model be what must be true of the system for that technique to work. Then generate more techniques from that understanding.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inverse Abstraction (Deconstruction, or Instantiation)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Break into component pieces, in multiple directions
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Ex. Machine learning becomes Linear Algebra + Calculus + Probability Theory + Computer Science, which break into their own subregions&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Ex. Scientific Field becomes Major Papers + Categories of the topic + Conferences + Major Researchers + Quality Sites&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simplify Recursively&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First Principles
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ask what the underlying goal is for a space, and for what solutions would serve that goal. For each solution, think of the components necessary to make that solution happen.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;List
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Create a list of examples of the item being modeled.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Idea list technique
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Set 10m timer, write down 10 creative ideas in a given domain in time given.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Problem - Solution Framing -
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;List important problems in / with the domain. For each problem, suggest a solution. Then criticise the solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abstraction
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Get a list of examples of the thing being modeled, and look at what’s similar behind those many examples&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Book
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To construct a model from a book, skim through the book and write down every idea that appears multiple times.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Also works across a set of videos&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Also works across a set of academic papers&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Take the hierarchy from the table of contents&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Take 3-4 books / papers with quality models, and look to find overlap and compress them.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People Based Framings
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Visionaries / Leaders / Creators in a domain and their models for the space&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Characteristics of the people who spend time with the domain and what that says about how it’s been conceived&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Relationships between people&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Organization Based Framings
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Major organizations in a space, their road to prominence, their model of the domain and plans for action and progress&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Problem Solving - cut out all the skills / resources necessary to solve problems in a space. Then break down the components that make up those skills or resources, and systematically identify failure modes for problem solving in that space.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extension of working Model&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Internal - External [Extends Model-Technique Framing]
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For a model of a personal process, create a model for what’s happening and then generalize to group, or generalize the technique directly.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Synthesis
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Take 3-4 models built by other people (often in the form of the above, or in the form of books, or an online course). Then compare them side by side and compress them into a single strong model.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recursive Extension - Take a model, and create a model of each subcomponent of the model.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ex. For a list, take each listed item and create a model of it.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;systematizing-systematizing&quot;&gt;Systematizing Systematizing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples:
Systematized Predictive Modeling
Systematizing Creativity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Abstraction &amp;amp; Generalization) What kinds of x exist?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(Idea List) For each kind of x, idea list ways to do x&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Decomposition) How can x be broken into sub-parts?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(Abstraction) What are the functions of each of the sub-parts?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the goals of the system and what are paths that lead to the accomplishment of those goals?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optimize over sub-parts of x&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recombine sub-parts of x
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Take the functional representation of sub-parts of x and generate new sub-parts or combinations of sub-parts that perform the same function&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;List the goals of the system
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Generate feedback processes for each goal, using its associated metrics&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blow the system up and cut the system down
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add every conceivable valuable module to the system, under time pressure for generating those hypotheses.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Triage, cutting the system down to its most valuable parts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Create long and short term / large and small versions of the system&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look at the way the system grounds out in low level behaviors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think about the way information needs to flow between different parts of the system, and at which points in time, and with which dependencies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systematize(x) &amp;lt;- write this function&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;def Decompose(x):&lt;br /&gt;
	* What kinds of x exist?&lt;br /&gt;
	* In what ways can you do x?&lt;br /&gt;
	* How can x be broken into sub-parts?&lt;br /&gt;
		* What are the functions of each of the sub-parts?&lt;br /&gt;
	* What are the goals of the system and what are paths that lead to the accomplishment of those goals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;def Systematize(x):&lt;br /&gt;
	* Decompose(x)&lt;br /&gt;
	* Optimize over sub-parts of (x)&lt;br /&gt;
	* Recombine sub-parts of (x)&lt;br /&gt;
	* Take the functional representation of sub-parts of x and generate new sub-parts or combinations of sub-parts that perform the same function&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decompose the problem into sub-problems.
Write down algorithms that correctly identify the sub-problems.
Write down high-level solutions.
Decompose the high-level solutions into lower level, specific algorithms that solve the sub-problems.
Compose those algorithms into a system that addresses the overall problem.
Feedback on each part of your system using metrics that direct valuable adaptations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;generating-generators&quot;&gt;Generating Generators&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an algorithm for generating systematizing creativity that I like to describe as to carefully watch a brilliant mind generate creative ideas, and then to 1. through seeing patterns and similarities among the generated ideas, categorize them and 2. create categories for the thought processes or mental motions that generated the ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are two generators of generators.&lt;br /&gt;
What else exists?&lt;br /&gt;
(Note, these are general enough to be meta-generators)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Categorize ideas using some pattern or notion of similarity. Use the examples to install the pattern, and look for the pattern elsewhere.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ex., you see attempts to establish control (over an idea, or a situation), attempts to find the optimal solution, attempts to break an idea down, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You turn these into generators by asking&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decompose a given pattern, seeing its variants, properties and types. Explicitly try to turn the pattern itself into a generator, as well as all of its decomposed variants.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recombine your generators with one another
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ex., what is the most general version of recombination?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If I look at differing types of recombination, how do they differ? In the process, in the inputs, in the outputs?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Read creative authors, subject them to a deep analysis of their conceptual style.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Listen abstractively to people speaking. Name / categorize the mental motions that lead to creative ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gather powerful solutions to important problems. Ask how / why they work. Turn their source of strength into a property of solutions / ideas that its worth incorporating or founding new solutions on. (Ex., data structures as re-representation / abstraction)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Watch your own thought, especially when you’ve solved something or generated something new. Ask after the prompts that lead to that path of thought.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;List the most powerful ideas.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ask, how could I have come up with this, or seen this pattern for the first time?
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Ask, how can I see this pattern more often when it comes up, and how does that process of pattern recognition work?
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Often, by seeing many examples of a pattern, you mind starts to pick it up much more easily. So to see patterns that others haven’t seen, look at data that others haven’t looked at.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn to see the incompleteness of things (frameworks, conceptual schemes, say checking for collective exhaustiveness, or searching for datapoints that don’t fit) and complete them (or rework the ontology entirely)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Apply this to systematizing creativity, taking creative ideas that can’t be explained as a call to enlargen the technical toolset, or make existing techniques more flexible&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create your own concepts, elucidate them in some detail, name them, and then see what patterns exist in your concept creation.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This is general to all creative work. Start creating, and watch yourself closely.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Jeremy Nixon</name></author><summary type="html">Meta-Modeling</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Counterfactual Value</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/08/03/counterfactual-value.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Counterfactual Value" /><published>2019-08-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-08-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/08/03/counterfactual-value</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/08/03/counterfactual-value.html">&lt;p&gt;There are a few ideas that can completely change your decision making and behavior. This is one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say you’re somebody who cares about having an impact in the world. It’s possible to have an entire life devoted to your loved cause (say, by becoming a physician and serving thousands of patients) which turns out to be an utter waste because you didn’t consider this concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question that matters for impact is ‘what would happen if I didn’t take this action?’. That question leads to very different outcomes. You may not realize that medical school admissions are capped, and so you’re not increasing the total number of physicians by going into medicine (but rather just replacing the person who barely got into your medical school with yourself).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The counterfactual impact on each of the patients you serve isn’t that they don’t get seen. It’s that they get seen by the person they’d have gone to if you weren’t there, or who would have been hired in your place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is general across all areas where impact is possible. Some companies wouldn’t have been founded otherwise - some would have. Some politicians are cookie cutter replacements of one another. The counterfactual impact question is a very different question than the impact question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many positions create value no matter who is in the position. It can be very difficult to disentangle the value of the particular person in the position from the position’s default value. And critically, the economy values the position much more than the person. There is certainly some room to argue that counterfactual impact also goes up with compensation, but often these are zero sum or near-zero sum games. Many jobs are about beating the competition and contribute nothing (think lawyers advocating for one company over another, or marketing and sales professionals pushing one product over another). All of this activity is nearly impactless from an impact perspective, despite there being dramatic sums paid to the parties on each side. The value paid can far outstrip counterfactual value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way this affects personal decision making is you need to think about how to build the company that wouldn’t be built if you didn’t build it, rather than just asking which company to build. You need to ask what research wouldn’t be done if you didn’t build it, or wouldn’t be popularized if you didn’t popularize it.
An extension to collective behavior is asking how to reward people for counterfactual impact rather than for objective impact. At scale, a redesign of capitalism structured around this new notion of value would produce societies that dramatically outcompeted our own, and our market mechanisms would be obsolete in comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to self: Write some science fiction where this mechanism has been discovered, and describe what happens to each kind of society.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jeremy Nixon</name></author><summary type="html">There are a few ideas that can completely change your decision making and behavior. This is one of them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Compressing Decision Making</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/07/29/decision-making.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Compressing Decision Making" /><published>2019-07-29T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/07/29/decision-making</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/07/29/decision-making.html">&lt;p&gt;Major Models&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learning from Failure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Facing Reality vs. Pretending / Ignoring Reality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Determination / Courage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social Norms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Opportunity Cost&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Triage / Prioritization (80/20 Pareto Principle)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Techniques&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to underlying reasons for the decision, and reason up. Goal Factor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a new person walked into your life, what would they do? Escape your mental frame.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When possible, run a trial of important decision before committing to them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Define and enshrine core priorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Premortem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What would the most determined, courageous version of me do?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zero Based Thinking
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If I was not already in this job / relationship / situation, would I enter it again?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If any variant of no, ask: How do I get out, and how quickly can I do it?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minor Models&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Confirmation Bias&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Short term emotions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prevention Focus vs. Promotion Focus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify and don’t tolerate the problems that stand in the way of your goals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design plans that explicitly lay out the tasks that will get you over your problems and onto your goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minor Techniques&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find objective Information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Distance yourself emotionally from the decision
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Worst case scenario&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimize the downside of your decision&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set tripwires to check whether a decision needs to be made / changed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Assume you can’t choose any of the existing options. What would you do?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Assume you’re forced into one decision. What would you do?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have multiple good options in front of you simultaneously (Protects from premature commitment)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seriously consider the opposite on important decisions. Find a belief driving your behavior and argue with all energy against it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look at your decision from the perspective of several time frames. 10 days / 10 months / 10 years, for example.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When you have a difficult decision to make, flesh it out as a values conflict&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Honestly ask yourself what you want and what should be done about it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What am I likely to lie to myself about in this space?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Jeremy Nixon</name></author><summary type="html">Major Models Learning from Failure Facing Reality vs. Pretending / Ignoring Reality Determination / Courage Social Norms Opportunity Cost Triage / Prioritization (80/20 Pareto Principle) Major Techniques Go to underlying reasons for the decision, and reason up. Goal Factor. If a new person walked into your life, what would they do? Escape your mental frame. When possible, run a trial of important decision before committing to them. Define and enshrine core priorities Premortem What would the most determined, courageous version of me do? Zero Based Thinking If I was not already in this job / relationship / situation, would I enter it again? If any variant of no, ask: How do I get out, and how quickly can I do it? Minor Models Confirmation Bias Short term emotions Prevention Focus vs. Promotion Focus Identify and don’t tolerate the problems that stand in the way of your goals Design plans that explicitly lay out the tasks that will get you over your problems and onto your goals Minor Techniques Find objective Information Distance yourself emotionally from the decision Worst case scenario Minimize the downside of your decision Set tripwires to check whether a decision needs to be made / changed Assume you can’t choose any of the existing options. What would you do? Assume you’re forced into one decision. What would you do? Have multiple good options in front of you simultaneously (Protects from premature commitment) Seriously consider the opposite on important decisions. Find a belief driving your behavior and argue with all energy against it. Look at your decision from the perspective of several time frames. 10 days / 10 months / 10 years, for example. When you have a difficult decision to make, flesh it out as a values conflict Honestly ask yourself what you want and what should be done about it. What am I likely to lie to myself about in this space?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Low Level Social Accountability</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/06/23/productivity-coach.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Low Level Social Accountability" /><published>2019-06-23T05:02:46-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-23T05:02:46-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/06/23/productivity-coach</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/06/23/productivity-coach.html">&lt;p&gt;The problem of behavioral control, or making sure that you do what you want to be doing in any given moment, is a cornerstone of productivity and effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to describe a lifestyle change that increased my productivity by 4x, going end-to-end in 3 weeks on a project that would normally have taken 4 months. I hired someone to be by my side, physically in person, all throughout work and make sure, in every moment, that I do exactly what I said I should be doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, we ran a productivity tracking system together inside a spreadsheet. Cutting the work session into 1 hour chunks, we would specify:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The set goal or goals for that hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A run through a checklist blocking potential distractions. Specifically:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Earplugs in&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Headphones over earplugs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Phone off and away&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wifi off (if possible)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Laptop away (if possible, when working on desktop)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first low-level action steps to take.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exactly which applications, websites, and tools were allowable for the work session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of one work session on the spreadsheet:
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/spreadsheet.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any deviation from working on the goal, say picking up my phone, wandering around, checking or responding to an email or message, eating / snacking while working, and many others would immediately be met by a hand on my shoulder and the question: is this in line with the goal you set? If the answer was no, the protocol is to immediately redirect my attention to the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the work session, we would track distractions. This was divided into external distractions (messages, people talking nearby, or talking to the low level social accountability / productivity coach) and internal distractions (spontaneously opening a website misaligned from the goal, distracting thoughts about personal life, and other internally generated distractions). Any repeating distraction would lead to the creation of a simple plan to eliminate the possibility of the distraction occuring again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2m after the work session we would reflect on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus intensity (a subjective 1-10 measure of the intensity of my focus)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time on Task (the fraction of time allocated that I actually spent focused on the task)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whether the goal was achieved or not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Layered on top of this was execution on a shortlist of the best hits from the productivity literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run Task Management System (Hierarchical Goals - Yearly - Monthly - Weekly - Daily)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Plan each day in advance&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Schedule on a calendar in addition to a to-do list&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus Tracking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time Tracking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bite off the smallest action step possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build streaks / habits / momentum&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Single, clear task at a time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most important task in the morning with focus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do the most difficult task first&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cut off all distractions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enter the appropriate mental state
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Music&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Visualization&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create Large Chunks of Time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social Accountability
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Precommitment&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Feedback&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many small projects - large projects kill morale&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Metrics as a reward system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set Deadlines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In line with many of these principles, this system works because it creates immense clarity which cuts through ambiguity and allows for decisive decision making, frees mindspace from distractions, and so enables entrance to a deeply focused state of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I experimented with variants of this which involved a remote watcher, both through screen capture and messaging back and forth on the hour. There were gains with these experiments but they weren’t nearly as substantial (my subjective estimates are ~1.5x w/ screen capture and ~1.3x with messaging). The price point was ~$600 / week. For me, this was more than worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jeremy Nixon</name></author><summary type="html">The problem of behavioral control, or making sure that you do what you want to be doing in any given moment, is a cornerstone of productivity and effectiveness.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Modes of Thinking worth Internalizing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/02/17/modes-of-thinking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modes of Thinking worth Internalizing" /><published>2019-02-17T16:42:46-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-17T16:42:46-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/02/17/modes-of-thinking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/02/17/modes-of-thinking.html">&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Latticework of Mental Models&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ex., pushing &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1QrrdKv267dlpy3sEVPvsRb-iZTyFKfr2mF5Wms4od3k/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;How to Think&lt;/a&gt; into intuition&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Systematizing Creativity&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ex., Reframing, Questioning Assumptions, Abstraction &amp;amp; Generalization, Decomposition, Composition / Recombination, Generators, Leading Questions, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Filter at the Intersection of Competing Worldviews&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Ex., &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1OrJDg3Y5s1g91kLsc2zVHJnZjjHbNTx8ZuHxbE20x20/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Worldview Building&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Ex., Internalizing the conceptual style of intellectual giants&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Intelligence Decomposition &amp;amp; Optimization Along All Axes&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Memory (Working, Episodic, Long Term)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Attention (though this feels like a limitation)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Having a model&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Abstract Knowledge Representation&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Ability to Generalize&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Learning / Adaptivity&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Creativity&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Information processing / Computation speed&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Goal accomplishment&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Technical Consilience (Seeing the unity of knowledge behind every natural science) by internalizing:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Information Theory (Cover / Thomas)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Statistical Mechanics (Talman)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Algorithmic Game Theory (Nisan)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Nonlinear Dynamics and Chaos (Strogatz)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Mechanism Design (Borgers)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Algorithms (CLRS)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Neuroscience (Principles of Neural Science)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Electromagnetics (Haliday / Resnick)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Quantum Mechanics (Griffiths)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Nuclear Physics (Krane)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Chemistry (Brown)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Intro Proof (How to Prove It)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Analysis (Abbott)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Set Theory (Halmus)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Abstract Algebra (Dummit, Foote)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Topology (Munkres)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Category Theory (Pierce, then Awodey)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Probability Theory: The Logic of Science (Jaynes)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Machine Learning: A Probabilistic Perspective&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Computational Learning Theory (Kearns)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Learning Invariant Representations (Poggio)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Causality (Pearl)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Computability and Logic (Boolos)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thinking and Deciding (Baron)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Types of thinking&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;On the Study of thinking (meta)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Rationality&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Logic&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Normative Theory of Probability&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Descriptive theory of probability judgment&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Hypothesis Testing&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Judgement of correlation and contingency&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Actively open-minded thinking&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Normative theory of choice under uncertainty&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Descriptive theory of choice under uncertainty&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Choice under certainty&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Utility Measurement&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Decision Analysis and Values&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Quantitative Judgment&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Moral judgment and choice&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Fairness and Justice&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Social Dilemmas: Cooperation vs. Defection&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Decisions about the future&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Risk&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Path to Awakening / Enlightenment, ex. the intersection of:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Shinzen Young’s The Science of Enlightenment&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Calduasa’s The Mind Illuminated&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Chapman’s Meaningness&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Wallis’s Trantra Illuminated&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Ingram’s Mastering the Core Teachings of the Buddha&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Discover and internalize lost philosophical traditions&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ex., Al Gazali, Mohisim, Presocratics, I Ching&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rationalism (May be too similar to Thinking and Deciding…)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;As framed in SSC / LW / Sequences / HPMOR / Inadequate Equilibria&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turn machine learning into a fully fledged philosophy around how to think (May be a subset of technical concilience…)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Bias-Variance Tradeoff&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ol&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Overfitting&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Controlling complexity&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;ol&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Model simplicity (restriction methods)&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Selection methods (over features)&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Regularization&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Curse of dimensionality&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Ensemble Modeling&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Occam’s Razor (Formalized)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Training vs. Generalization Error&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Interpolation vs. Extrapolation&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Smoothness&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;VC Dimension&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Variance Maximization&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ol&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Optimizing for Volatility vs Expected Value&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Bayes Rule&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Bayes Error&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Exploration-Exploitation&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Manifolds as Data Representation&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Jeremy Nixon</name></author><summary type="html">Latticework of Mental Models</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Generators of Felt-Sense Meaning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/02/17/generators-of-meaning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Generators of Felt-Sense Meaning" /><published>2019-02-17T14:09:46-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-17T14:09:46-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/02/17/generators-of-meaning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/02/17/generators-of-meaning.html">&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Human connection (Especially its creation, its loss)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Family&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Sense of belonging, of home&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Community&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Friendship&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Bonding&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Romantic Pair Bonding&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mission&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Working towards / for something larger than yourself&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Sacrifice&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Investment&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Collective Mission / Movements&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Specialness&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Being, feeling special&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Religion&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Sacred Beliefs&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Higher than humanity, transcendence&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Enlightenment / Awakening&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Immortality&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Denial of Death&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Live on in works and impact&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Suffering&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Avoidance of suffering, in self and others&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Elimination of suffering&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Knowledge &amp;amp; Insight&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Identity&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Changes in identity&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Purpose Fulfillment&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Destruction / Creation of Identity&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Growth&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Autonomy / Control / Responsibility&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Jeremy Nixon</name></author><summary type="html">Human connection (Especially its creation, its loss)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Become Obsessed</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/02/08/obsessed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Become Obsessed" /><published>2019-02-08T19:44:46-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-08T19:44:46-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/02/08/obsessed</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2019/02/08/obsessed.html">&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Social Immersion&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Existential Importance&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Long term future&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Moral righteousness about it - nobody is doing this the right way&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vivid vision of the future&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expectations for oneself being high.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Narrative alignment&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Associate your identity with your performance / knowledge&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have an enemy who’s growing faster than you are&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a competition that you can win&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Win competitions and get addicted to winning&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Find ways to visceral reward yourself for success in the domain&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vision - see yourself as reifying becoming truly great / transcending and achieving complete mastery of the target&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Listen to the Voice of God&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lifestyle immersion&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Sound / Audiobook / Podcasts on obsessive topic, for use during transit&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Create friendships around topic, turn social time into conversation over obsession target&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Go to sleep reading about it&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Write about it during free writing&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Create reputation around it&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Feel yourself growing at it&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Jeremy Nixon</name></author><summary type="html">Social Immersion Existential Importance</summary></entry></feed>